我所爱的李慕白已经死去18年了
It has been 18 years since the death of my beloved Li Mu Bai.
那段时间里     侠义之士
In that time,the followers of the Iron Way
变得越来越少
have become few and far between.
武林中人不断争权夺利
Warring clans now vie for power over the Martial World.
我却希望能被武林所遗忘
It is into this world that I hope to slip unnoticed...
就像一个被遗忘的鬼魂一样
like a forgotten ghost
Name：Personnel are rubbish
据说一位学者的声名
It is said that a scholar's name will last
在他死后会持续5年
for five years beyond his passing...
一位剑客的名字会被铭记20年
and a swordsman will be remembered for 20 years.
这似乎意味着赞美...
This is meant as praise...
但我相信这是一种祸害
but I believe it to be a curse.
这是谁?
Well, what have we here?
这个女人说她想加入本派
This girl claims she wants to join our ranks.
守卫在山门前发现了她
The guards found her at the temple gate.
你为何而来？
What brings you here?
我找西莲派的戴阎王
I seek Hades Dai of the West Lotus.
一个可以一统武林的高人
A man great enough to rule the Martial World.
现在你已经看到他了     你有什么要说的？
And now you have found him. What would you ask of me?
让她走
Let her go!
直到值得被我杀死
Let her grow into someone worth killing.
魏方
Wei-Fang.
现身！
Show yourself!
你是谁
Who are you?
问她
Ask her.
魏方
Wei-Fang
你是谁？
Who are you?
带我去见戴阎王     我会给他一个预料之外的惊喜
Bring me to Lord Dai and I will give him a prize greater than the one he sought.
主子     俞师傅已经到了
Master Yu has arrived, sir.
秀莲
Xiu Lien.
你算是悲痛日子里的一点安慰
You brighten a sad day.
你以前住的客房我特意留了下来
I've ensured your old quarters were kept for you.
我知道你一定会来
I knew you would come.
你不是唯一知道的人
You were not the only one.
我在路上被袭击了
I was attacked along the way.
先父辞世后       武林中已有数十个剑客被杀
Two dozen swordsmen slain since my father passed.
即便是像你这样的高手    戴阎王也毫无所忌
Hades Dai knows no fear to attack a warrior as great as you.
你于危险之中我也很难过
I'm sorry you were put at risk.
分担贝勒府的悲痛      我也是理所应当
It is my duty to be here,to share your family's loss.
共承悲痛
Our loss.
我父亲总是待你像家人一样
My father always regarded you as family.
它没有被藏起来
It is not kept hidden.
在家父最后的一年里    想把它放到一个看得到的地方
In his last year,my father wanted it where he could see it.
会让他想起了更多难忘的日子
It reminded him of more noble days.
它有着这么多不幸的事
It bears so many sorrows.
最难忘的是
One above all.
李慕白
Li Mu Bai.
我曾是他的学生    那时你们都在这儿
I was his student when you were both here.
他的死触动了我们所有人
His death touched us all.
我父亲    他以为你们会共结连理
My father, he thought you would wed.
我们不会
We could not.
我和另一个人已有婚约
I was promised to another.
它应该被藏起来
It should be locked away.
铁贝勒已经死了
A great lord has died,
你想利用这段混乱的时间
and you seek to use this time of chaos
成为武林至尊
to emerge as the one true leader of the Martial World.
你能看透我的心思？
Do you read my mind?
我能看到你的野心
No. Your ambition.
那把刀很好
This sword is great,
但还有一把更好的
but there is one greater.
青冥宝剑
The Green Destiny.
青冥宝剑已经消失了很多年了
The Green Destiny was lost long years ago.
并没有消失     是被藏了起来
Not lost. Hidden.
就在铁贝勒府
Kept by the House of Te.
我该在贝勒府掀起一场血雨腥风吗？
Am I to storm the home of the Emperor's brother?
只需要让一个人去即可
Send instead a single drop of rain.
他
The boy...
他失败了一次     刚刚爬回家
who crawled home from failure?
那不是魏方一个人的错
The fault is not Wei-Fang's alone.
他武艺尚浅
His training is not complete.
让他去做这件事无异于自杀
To send him on this mission alone would be suicide.
也许我可以
Perhaps I can-
是他带我来见你
He brought me to you.
让他去
Send the boy.
他和剑的命运是束缚在一起的
He and the sword are bound by fate.
我已经看到了
I have seen it.
那位年轻的小姐是谁
Who is that young lady?
我想是位官员的女儿
I believe the daughter of an official.
有很多人前来吊丧
Many have come to pay their respects.
贼！  家里进贼了！
Thief! Thief in the house!
这人是谁？
Who is this man?
我听到些动静
I heard a disturbance.
他试图偷剑
He was trying to steal the sword.
我试图偷...?
I was trying to steal--?
抓住他了
We caught the thief.
他不止是贼
He is more than a thief.
它是西莲派的      是他袭击了我的马车
He is West Lotus.He attacked my carriage.
把他带到衙门
Take him to the Marshal.
不     把他关在这里
No. Keep him here.
戴阎王不会随便指派个人来
Hades Dai would not assign this mission lightly.
如果这个人对他有价值      对我们也一样
If the boy has value to him,he may yet have value to us.
好吧
Very well.
把他关在院子里
Confine him and secure the compound.
会对这个男的做什么？
What will happen to him? The boy?
你是谁？
Who are you?
我叫雪瓶
I am called Snow Vase.
我来祭奠铁贝勒
I came to pay my respects to Sir Te.
你很关心这个贼？
And your concern for the thief?
只是对奇怪的事有些好奇
You mistake curiosity for concern.
这把剑像他们说的那般厉害吗？
Is it as powerful as they say?
在正确的人手里是
In the right hand.
教教我
Teach me.
你学的够好了
You have been well taught already.
我想学更多武艺
I want to learn more.
像你这般
I want to walk the path you followed.
我会照顾你一辈子
I will serve you for life.
我不需要丫环      雪瓶
I don't need a servant, Snow Vase.
我一向独来独往      并且很快会回到这种生活
My life is solitude,and I return to it shortly.
如果你想寻求一位师父的话      请到别处
If you seek a teacher,you must look elsewhere.
这么冷的一夜      都不能让你松口？
Did a night in the cold loosen your tongue?
把笼子打开      我会把你的牙打掉
Open this cage and I'll loosen your teeth.
够了
That's enough!
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
魏方
Wei-Fang.
戴阎王想要那把剑？
So, Hades Dai wants the sword？
现在让我带这把剑走      你们还有一条活路
Let me leave with the sword now and you'll be spared.
否则    血染贝勒府
Otherwise, this house will swim with blood.
必须给皇上送个口信
Word must be sent to the Emperor.
京城以南恐有争斗
There is war in the south.
我不能以江湖纷争打扰他
I cannot trouble him with these underworld affairs.
皇上也从不听信我们父子的只言片语
The Emperor doesn't heed my words as he did my father's.
剑必须马上转移走
The sword must be removed from here at once.
它在这里很安全    秀莲
It is safest here, Xiu Lien.
如果西莲派要夺走它      放在哪里都不安全
Nothing is safe if West Lotus claims that sword.
剑必须被带到武当派藏于山中
It must be taken to Wudang Temple,high up in the mountains.
不   我曾对先父起誓
No. I made an oath to my father
将青冥宝剑守护在贝勒府
that I would guard and protect the Green Destiny within these walls.
铁贝勒在天之灵会明白的
Sir Te would understand.
你作为一家之主      众人尊敬
You've earned your place in this house and much respect beyond.
只有你这么说    秀莲
Only from you, Xiu Lien.
一直没变
It was always that way.
你先听我说
Then listen to me now.
假如戴阎王真的来了      他只会鸡犬不留
If Hades Dai comes here,he'll leave nothing standing.
没有人会活下去      我们没有别的选择
No one alive.We have no choice.
我对我父亲的誓言      是我受人尊敬的根本
The promise that I made my father is all I have to earn honor in this house.
这才是我余生最重要的     秀莲
It is worth my life, Xiu Lien.
我们必须让客人离开
We must ask the guests to leave.
你会留在这里吗？     你与我父亲总是互帮互助
Will you stay? You always came to my father's aid and he to yours.
你会帮我吗？
Will you help?
只要需要      我会一直留在这里
I will stay as long as I am needed.
我会恳请客人离开
I will bid the guests to leave.
留下那个喊贼的女人
Keep the girl who caught the thief.
她让我教他武艺
She has asked me to teach her...
但是我怀疑她另有所想
but I suspect she can teach us.
我们也需要更多的兵器
We will need more arms.
我会补充护卫
I will hire extra guards.
我们需要的不是简单的护卫
We need those who will do more than guard.
而是一些侠义之士
There are warriors who once stood against this type of injustice.
肝胆相照
True followers will still answer the call.
侠义不只是道听途说...
The Iron Way is not legend...
远远不是
not yet.
我告诉你      我很讲信用
I'm telling you, I'm good for it.
你根本就是言而无信
You are good for nothing.
我们就是告示上要找的人
We're good for your warrant.
我有29个弟兄      每个人头20两纹银
I have 30 swords at 20 ounces of silver a head.
那是...
That's...
600两纹银...     可惜了
six hundred ounces of silver... wasted.
铁贝勒文武双全      受人敬仰
Sir Te was honored by masters of pen and sword alike.
如果他的家人需要      侠肝义胆之士都会相应其号召
If his house has need, men of the Iron Way should heed for the honor of his cause,
不取分毫
not promise of riches.
这位朋友说得好
My friend is right.
这告示不是给你看的
This warrant is not for you.
如果我说是哪？
And if I say it is?
想想再说
Think about it.
别急于说出口
They're not that fast.
大言不惭...     就凭你
Big words for a little man...all alone.
他可不是一个人
He's not alone.
我和他一起的
I stand with him.
山东飞刀    愿听差遣
Flying Blade of Shantung,at your service.
我也一样
As am I.
浙江 - 陈一雷
Thunder Fist Chan, famed in Zhejiang.
还有我
And I,
福州 - 史银镖
Silver Dart Shi.Famed in Fuzhou.
还有我    马贵      四海为家
And I, Turtle Ma.Famed in... this tavern.
你是谁
Who are you?
我被叫作独狼
I'm known as Silent Wolf.
看来桌子都要重做了
We'll have to rebuild all the tables!
是谁威胁着铁贝勒府
Who threatens the House of Te?
西莲派
West Lotus.
我需要一些侠客守护贝勒府
I need swords to protect its walls.
现在至少四个人了
Now you have four more.
算上我一个
To add to your army.
你需要多少个人
How many, in your army?
五个人
Five.
五百人
Hundred?
五个人
Five.
不断跑动可以一敌百
Well, better five that can fight than 500 that can run.
我想喝一杯
I need a drink.
不要钱    也别再回来了
On the house. Never come back.
我现在开始教你
Let the training begin.
不要只用眼看      也要用心听
Do not just watch with your eyes,listen with your mind.
再试一次
Again.
你对那个人很好奇
Your curiosity with the boy...
我不是好奇
I'm not curious.
难道是我看错了？
Then what do I now mistake for curiosity?
无可救药！
Hopeless!
多管闲事
Irritation.
必须在这练武吗？
Must we train here?
是
Yes.
一股脑儿可学不到真本事
True skill is not a blazing flame.
再试一次
Again.
过于努力了！
Too much blazing flame!
与你无关
This does not concern you!
即便你毁上千根木棍  上千把剑
A thousand broken sticks and swords
只要你不平心静气      什么也学不会
won't teach as much as the one that bends to your will.
无论怎样做都可以       只要碰得到我
Touch me, however you can.
对我也行
Or me!
别理他       来吧。
Ignore him. Strike me.
招式路数太明显了
The predictable attack has a predictable outcome.
再来
Again.
一直练习
Keep practicing.
要变幻莫测
Be unpredictable.
轻功
Light Body Skill.
你从哪学的
Where did you learn that?
我师傅教我的
My teacher. She taught me.
看起来你师傅是一个女人
So, your teacher was a woman.
她叫什么名字
What is her name?
你不会知道她的
You would not know it.
为什么你不跟她学的时间长一点
And why do you no longer study with her?
她死了
She died.
很多年了
Years ago.
我明白了
I see.
我会勤加练习
I will practice.
你不会白教的
Your patience will be rewarded.
也许你应该换一个大点的孔
Perhaps you need a bigger hole.
比如你那张一直张开的嘴
Like your mouth, which is always open.
倒是值得一试
I could try that.
也可以
You could try...
你也可以放我走
Or you could let me go.
放你走？   让你可以偷一次？
Let you go? So you can thieve again?
带着剑给那个大恶人戴阎王
Bring your spoils to that monster Hades Dai?
戴掌门是个十分厉害的人
Lord Dai is a great warrior.
在他的统领下      武林将会风平浪静
Under his hand,the Martial World will be peaceful.
你师傅是个杀人犯
Your master is a murderer.
啊，陈一雷
Ah, Thunder Fist Chan.
五两银子典当你的兵器对你来说       一定是件悲惨的事
Things must be quite dire for you to pledge your sword for five measly taels of silver.
这年头没镖压了吗？
No gold convoys going out this season?
我那是在保护我的兵器不被抢走
I was protecting that convoy from raiders,
尤其是你这种受雇的人
raiders that you hired out to.
那些来自浙江的拳手       总是找合适他们的理由
How these southern boxers from Zhejiang retell history when it suits them.
你在嘲笑浙江人吗？
You mock Zhejiang, do you?
别介意     我们都是为一件事聚才一起
Easy, boys.We have all been hired for the same cause.
但是有人确切的知道是什么吗？
But does anyone know what that is exactly?
因为我们都能喝吗？
All the wine we can drink?
我不敢苟同
I didn't hear that part, Ma.
算是原因之一
It was implied.
我听到些风言风语
I heard whispers that it's kept there.
铁贝勒府
In the House of Te.
青冥宝剑一直在那
The Green Destiny.
剑的铸造
The blade was forged
可以追溯到先秦
Forged with a technique that dates back to the Qin era.
锻造的方法没有传下来   (指吴国的揉剑法)
A technique lost to history.
由一种特殊材料锻造   (先秦的时候，有大马士革钢这种说法？)
A blade that could carve through Damascus steel.
最后手持这把剑的人在一场决斗中被击败了
Nobody who was wielding the blade was ever defeated in a duel or battle.
独狼       这是真的吗？
Silent Wolf, is this true?
我们是去守剑的吗？
Are we being hired to guard a sword?
我很好奇他怎么起了这么一个名字
I wonder how he got his name.
恭迎各位到来
I bid you welcome.
失陪了
Excuse me.
解释一下    一个人是怎样起死回生的
Explain how a man returns from the dead.
我们订婚了
We were to wed.
我也为你感到哀痛
I mourned for you.
秀莲
Xiu Lian
你不要说那个名字
That name is not yours to speak.
我在那场决斗之前心已经死了    很早以前
I was dead before that duel，Long before
我这么做是为了你和李慕白
I did it for you and Li Mu Bai.
我知道你爱的是他    不是我
I knew you loved him, not me.
我和戴阎王在灵鹫峰的决斗
When Hades Dai and I fought on Vulture's Peak...
是我唯一能看到的出路
...I took the only path I could see.
戴阎王以为我死了
Hades Dai left me for dead.
而我留在山上
I made my way to the mountains,
选择独自隐居
and chose a life of solitude.
在哪之前...     我发现慕白和我追求的...
Up there... I found what Mu Bai and I had strived for...
我无法面对...
detachment...
后来我想开了
enlightenment.
我离开     是因为我知道只要我还活着
I stayed away because I knew that as long as I was alive,
慕白是不会向你求婚的
Mu Bai would not ask you to marry him.
即便你死了
Nor in your death.
他也没有这么做
Such was his honor.
你装死什么意义也没有
You feigned your death for nothing.
不是装死
It wasn't feigned.
我切身感受到了
It was deeply felt.
那只是你一厢情愿      你让我们所有人都相信了
That was your choice,and you made it for all of us.
在你死后我已经心境平和了     以后也是
I have made peace with your passing, and so it will remain.
你留在这里       是因为需要你
You are needed and you're here.
你的本领和胆识还没有被忘记
Your skill and courage are not forgotten.
再无其他
All else is.
你是谁
And you are?
雪瓶
Snow Vase.
俞秀莲的徒弟
Student of Master Yu Shu Lien.
我还不知道她还有一个徒弟
I have not known her to take a student.
现在你知道了
So you know her well.
嗯
Well enough.
怎么了？
How?
这儿不是多说的地方
This is not the place for story.
那以后再说
Another time, then.
你师傅...
Your teacher...
她怎么样？
is she content?
她很伤心
She's in mourning.
我知道
Of course.
不只是因为铁贝勒
I do not speak just of Sir Te.
你动作真轻
You move as quietly as ever.
再轻你也听到了
Not so quiet that you will not hear.
你收了一个徒弟
You have taken a student.
是
Yes.
她和笼子里那个人       有些莫名的联系
They are connected somehow,she and that boy.
那个人走入歧途       但我能感到一颗单纯的心
He roars, but I feel a gentle soul may sleep within.
你的徒弟那？
And your student?
我不太确定
I am not certain.
我从她眼神里看到了一丝阴暗
I see darkness in her eyes.
对她可能是一个凶兆
She could be an even greater threat.
对我也是
To us...
这些守卫顶得住吗？
or those we guard against?
事后才能知道
Time will tell.
雪瓶的师傅可能是寒梅  (玉娇龙)
Her teacher may have been Han Mei,
背离武当的那个女侠
the renegade swordswoman from Willow Valley.
她已经死去很多年了
She's gone many years.
那她教雪瓶的时候一定很年轻
So she taught Snow Vase quite young.
太桀骜不驯
Too young.
雪瓶小姐？
Miss Snow Vase?
来和我们喝一杯
Raise a cup with us.
来吧
Yes, come in.
来吧,雪瓶？
Come on, Snow？
敬铁贝勒
Mm-hm. To Sir Te and to his House.
他们说一个能够拿起酒杯的女人     才是男人想要的女人
They say a woman who can hold her wine is a woman a man will want to hold.
谁说的？
Who says that?
我说的
I do.
我们喝酒是为了记起一些事
We drink to remember,
但是你们喝酒是为了忘记一些事
but it seems you drink to forget.
何从谈起？
How do you take the measure of a man?
你是从哪看出来的？
Which part of a man？
举手投足间
Ma, behave.
当我没问
I said nothing.
酒后胡言
The wine was asking.
那就别问
Ask your heart.
你说得对
I do. My head answers.
这会有惨烈的一仗
The greatest battle of them all.
你也不是独自一个人
And you are hardly the only who fights it here.
独狼在哪？
Where is Silent Wolf?
他和陈一雷在一起
He guards with Thunder Fist.
我想打听下     俞师傅     她有什么嗜好
So Master Yu, what is she like?
静下心来
Pierce its heart.
武艺的要诀是
True skill is a key in the moon.
耳听八方
Listen... with your nose.
眼观六路
A predictable attack has a predictable
你让我教你
You asked to be taught.
你就必须要明白        你要学的还有很多
And clearly,there is much you need to learn.
师傅        要做多久
How long, teacher?
这根木棍的影子从这到那
Until the shadow moves from here to there.
两次
Twice.
你学的很快
You learn quickly.
很好
That's good.
雪瓶        你对她了解多少
Snow Vase. How do you know her?
一点也不了解
I do not.
那她对你感兴趣
Then her interest in you?
你师傅说你对我有些兴趣        真的吗？
Your master believes you have interest in me. True?
说句话      我很无聊
Talk to me. I am bored.
孤独
Lonely.
与我无关
Neither is my problem.
如果有关那？
But what if you are their solution?
别说了
Stop talking.
如果你笑一个        我保证不再多说一句
A single smile and you have my word. I will fall silent.
你已经多说了一句        你怎么闭嘴？
How can you fall silent and yet give a word?
你为什么总是这么冰冷        没有一点笑容？
How can you hold so much wine and not smile?
这是红沙帮的地盘
This is territory allied to the Red Desert clan.
我们已经断了他们的后路
We have cut off their supply.
明晚
Come the New Moon,
西莲派会占据整个地盘
West Lotus will own this entire territory.
但也只不过是在灵宝
But this is merely Lingbao.
不是北京的贝勒府
Not Peking.
我会派一部分人去北京
Mantis will go where an army cannot.
而你们聚集在黄河边准备迎战
While you soldiers will gather at the Twin Rivers and prepare for war
面对武林中的所有对手
against all rival clans in the Martial World.
魏方没有做到的我会做到
I will succeed where Wei-Fang did not.
现在你看到了什么        先知？
What do you see now, prophet?
什么也没有
I see nothing,
但是我听到了一些
but I hear word.
就像你听到的        魏方会偷剑成功？
Just as you heard word that Wei-Fang would succeed in his raid?
再说错一次
Give another false prophecy,
你不仅会没有眼睛        舌头也会没有
you'll not only have no eyes, you'll have no tongue.
但那时你就不会知道贝勒府的贵客是谁了
But then you wouldn't know of the honored guest who now resides at the House of Te
一个死里逃生的人
One thought long dead has returned.
一雷守住南院
Thunder Fist will guard the south gate.
马贵        我们这很容易受到攻击
Turtle Ma,we are vulnerable here.
有人来了
Guard!
他们来救我了
They've come for me.
我才能救你
I've come for you.
他们只会鸡犬不留
They leave destruction,death in their wake.
你还和他们一起吗？
Do you still stand with them?
小心背后
Look out.
剑在哪？
Where's the sword?
他不知道
He does not know.
剑在东院
The sword is in the east courtyard.
一旦我拿到了剑       第一个要死的就是你
Once I hold the blade, you will be the first to fall.
你找不到的
You will not find it there,
剑在我这
nor take it from here.
俞师傅
Master Yu!
放他走
Let him go.
放开他
Release him.
把剑给我        否则就是他死
Give it to me now or he dies!
贝勒府也会没落
The House of Te will fall.
侠义之道也会随之没落
As will the followers of the Iron Way.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我父母被你手里的这把剑所杀
My parents were slain by the sword you hold.
每一个夜晚        我都能听到他们在地府叮嘱我
On clear nights, I still hear them calling to me from the other world.
只有一句话
One word...
报仇
vengeance.
为了那么一点小钱送死        多可怜啊！
Such a pity to die for a fee！
不是为了钱       是侠义
Not for gold, it's for the Iron Way.
我弟弟就是因此而死        一点也不值得
My brother died for the Iron Way.It was worthless.
你应该找个好点的理由
You should have found yourself a better cause,
或者像我一样
as I did.
史银镖！     滚开！
Shi! No! Get away from her!
马贵...
Turtle Ma...
史银镖
Silver Dart Shi.Famed in Fuzhou.
还有铁贝子    (贝勒的儿子叫贝子)
And now I mourn the death of Sir Te Zhao,
你我情同手足
the son of the man who was like a father to me.
所有这些都是因为一把剑
All this for a sword.
侠义、胆识、名望
Code, duty, honor.
他们都是因此而死
Excuses for bloodshed,all of them.
这就是我为什么看淡名利
That is why I left it behind.
心如止水
I was content.
置身其外了
Above it all.
现在我要做我该做的
And now a kite laments its return.
带着这把剑离开
I will take the sword and leave.
不       他们耳目众多
No. They watch the roads.
在这够安全了
It is safer here.
我不这么想
But I do not feel it.
到处都弥漫着仇恨
Not when vengeance chokes the air.
你救了我一命
You saved my life.
我知道
I spoke before I thought.
你很善良
Your words came from the heart.
你母亲
Your mother...
告诉我你知道的
tell me of her.
为什么？
Why?
她是什么样的人
What was she like?
我没有母亲
I have no mother.
我被西莲派的铁乌鸦抚养长大
I was raised by Iron Crow of West Lotus.
他竭尽所能的教我
He taught me everything I know,
就像你师傅教你一样
as your teacher taught you.
你学的很快
You learn fast.
很有天分
Knowledge is in your blood.
继续练
Again.
他让我感到亲情
He gave me a sense of purpose.
你母亲是凉州方知府的小妾
Your mother was a concubine.
这你一定知道
Or so you've been told.
你怎么知道
How do you
我知道你的过去
I know your past.
谁告诉你这些的
Who told you this?
一位赫赫有名的女侠
A swordswoman of great renown.
你真正的母亲叫做寒梅    (玉娇龙)
Your real mother was known as Han Mei.
一个受过难以估量痛苦的女人。
A woman who had felt and brought immeasurable pain.
她怀着的你
In her womb, she carried you,
是她所爱的男人的最后一晚留下来的
the legacy from her last night with the man she loved.
她怀的是一个男孩
Great is the joy of a child,
并且有一个胎记
greater still, the value of a boy.
当她睡下的时候
While she slept,
前几天客栈里一个生了一个女儿的小妾
a concubine who had given birth to a daughter there days before...
把你换成了那个女孩...
switched her worthless girl for you...
如果她生出一个男孩的话       就能取悦他的丈夫
hoping it would please her master if she presented him with a son.
当寒梅发现的时候已经晚了
When Han Mei realized what had been done...
她本来打算抛弃这个女孩
she meant to abandon the girl.
但是于心不忍
But her heart refused.
她尝试着忘记你
She tried to wash from her skin he blood she had shed.
但是你母亲无法摆脱这份骨肉之痛
But your mother could not be rid of the pain she had caused in her life.
她视我如己出
She raised me as her own.
授我侠义之道
Trained me in the Iron Way.
那女人...     我母亲
The woman... My mother...
有找过我吗？
Did she look for me?
她每时每刻都在找你
Every minute of every day she searched.
她打听到那个小妾为了保命       把你给了西莲派
She learned the concubine had given you to West Lotus to save her own life.
为了找回你她挑战戴阎王
She challenged Hades Dai for your freedom.
她画下了你的胎记叮嘱我找到你
She showed me your birth markand said, "You must find him.
如果你是一个好人       就共扶侠义
If he is a good man, stand beside him.
如果你是个坏人
If he has become a poison dragon...
就杀了你
kill him."
你母亲
Your mother,
我师傅
my teacher...
因找你而死
died trying to find you.
这就是你我的故事
That is our story, yours and mine.
等等
Wait.
回来
Come back!
这是为了史银镖
This is for Shi!
这是为了马贵
And this is for Ma!
停手
Stop!
他是西莲派的人
He is one of them!
她说得对
She's right!
这不是我们做事的方式
This is not our way.
如果你要争斗       就应该公平一些
If you're going to fight, fight like men.
够了
Enough!
有人把你教的很好
Someone taught you well.
还不够好
Not well enough.
师傅？
Teacher?
进来
Come in.
你要走了
You're leaving.
剑不能留在这儿
The sword cannot be kept here.
你要把它带到哪？
Where are you taking it?
我不会告诉你的       太多人想得到它了
I would not burden you with that knowledge. Too many will hunt it.
我能和你一起走吗？
Can I go with you?
不行
No.
我必须孤身一人
I must make this journey alone.
独狼那？
What about Silent Wolf?
跟你一起走吗？
Will he go?
他为什么要跟我一起走
Why should he?
我以为你们要一起走
I see the way you are together.
你不再信任他了吗？
Is it that you don't trust him anymore?
你说信任？
You speak of trust?
你的师傅是寒梅
You, whose teacher who was Han Mei.
你一直都知道？
You always knew?
她在武当学的轻功
She learned her skills at Wudang.
然后用它偷学武术背离武当
Then chose to use them for her own gain as an outlaw on the run.
你以为我看不到你在步她的后尘吗？
You think I wouldn't see her shadow on your sword?
我想把你从她的命运中拉出来
I wanted to save you from her fate.
你对她一无所知
You know nothing of her fate.
她死于那个屠夫戴阎王之手
Her life was lost to that butcher, Hades Dai.
我想学艺用着把剑为她报仇
I sought the sword and your teachings to avenge her.
雪瓶     你心中太多的仇恨
Do not carry vengeance in your heart, Snow
你让我忘掉过去
You tell me to let go of my past.
独狼一直在你身边       你也同样什么都没做
Silent Wolf waits for you and yet you do nothing.
你也没什么勇气面对
So much for your legendary courage.
我的人生不会再变了
My path is set.
你还年轻
You are still young.
你可以
Yours is not.
我知道我该做什么
I know what I must do.
史银镖
Silver Dart Shi.
她比我们更有勇气
She had more courage than any one of us.
马贵
Turtle Ma.
我从没想到我会这么说       我会想你的
I never thought I'd be saying this, but I'm going to miss him.
多倒一点
Pour him a double.
你知道吗       在四川截镖的时候
You know, at the Battle of Sichuan,
我也袭击过
I did hire out to those raiders.
但是我做的是劫富济贫
But only because I thought that they were doing the right thing.
我明白
I know that.
我心里清楚
Always did.
而你是押镖的
And you hired out to that gold convoy for the same reason.
侠义之道
The Iron Way...
我们一直因它而活
some of us never stop living by it.
甚至也会因它而死
Even if it meant dying by it.
我来这是为了祭奠铁贝勒
I came here to pay my respects to Sir Te.
而现在...
And now...
也为他儿子感到哀痛
I mourn for his son.
今夜...       我要带剑离开
Tonight... I leave with the sword.
独狼那？
And Silent Wolf?
你会告诉他吗？
Will you speak with him?
我会守住这把剑的
I'll guard the sword.
你背叛了戴阎王
You betrayed Hades Dai, boy.
她值得你这么做吗？
Is she worth your life?
你的师傅吗
And that of your teacher?
把剑带给戴阎王，否则你师傅铁乌鸦死路一条
Bring Hades Dai the sword or your Master, Iron Crow, dies.
现在他已经去找你了，把剑带回来
Even now, he rides to meet you and secure the sword.
我一定要带着剑走       你知道的
I cannot leave without the sword.You know this.
如果带剑走的话       你会被杀死的
You will be killed if you take it.
如果我不带剑走的话也会被杀死
- I will be killed if I don't.
那就走的远远的
Then go!
离西莲派越远越好
Far from here,far from West Lotus Temple.
我遵守了对你母亲承诺
I fulfilled my promise to your mother.
现在你一定要答应我不再回来
Now you must promise me to never return.
好
I promise.
我看丢他了
I never saw him.
一个人打了我       然后我就没知觉了
Felt a hand on my arm,then I could not move.
发生了什么事
What happened?
剑丢了
The sword.
那人偷走了它
The boy escaped and stole it.
你的命在你手中       别再走了
You hold your life in your hand. Think of that.
不止我一个人的命
It is not my life I hold this for.
走     活着把剑带走
Go! Take the sword and save yourself.
用你的命保住这把剑
Protect the sword with your life!
师傅！
Teacher!
走
Go!
撑住
Be still.
我很好
I am all right.
我先把血止住
Let me stop the bleeding.
秀莲
Xiu Lien...
我又一次失信了
I have failed you again.
你已经做了很多了       现在该我做出选择了
You made your choice all those years ago.Now I will make my choice.
来匡扶侠义之道       尽管会因其而死
To live the Iron Way,may be to die for it.
我会与你奋战到底
I would rather face an army by your side...
共赴黄泉
than to live another day without you.
你的预言是对的
Your prophecy is proven.
你师傅会为你感到骄傲
Your teacher would be proud.
我母亲也是
And my mother as well.
一个曾经被我杀死的人竟然回来挑战我？
How does a man I once killed return to challenge me?
和我一起在黑暗里吧       秀莲
Come with me into the dark,Xiu Lien.
我们会送你归西
We will have our vengeance on you.
去见你爱的李慕白
Now you will join your beloved, Li Mu Bai.
我们尚未握着这把剑
We don't hold this sword.
这把剑却已握着我们
This sword holds us.
我不能失去你
No. I can't lose you.
不
No.
你不要死
You must fight.
活下去
Stay with us.
这就是所说的       一位女侠的名号
It is said that a swordsman's name
可以影响其后20年
will last for twenty years beyond his passing.
但是我相信另一些人的名字也不会被忘记
But I believe that some names will live forever.
山东飞刀
Flying Blade of Shantung.
听候差遣
At your service.
浙江 - 陈一雷
Thunder Fist Chan, famed in Zhejiang.
福州 - 史银镖
Silver Dart Shi. Famed in Fuzhou.
马贵       四海为家
Turtle Ma. Famed in... this tavern.
我是俞秀莲
I am Yu Shu Lien,famed in Peking.
这是孟思昭
He is Meng Si Zhao.
也被称作独狼
Known as Silent Wolf in the west.
这是魏方
He is Wei-Fang,
已经弃暗投明
who found his way back through the dark.
她是雪瓶
She is Snow Vase,
履行了他的诺言
the warrior who fulfilled her vow...
并把他带回了侠义之道
and brought redemption to the woman who raised her in the Iron Way.
我们把剑带到了武当山       那里会是安全的地方
We take the sword to Wudang Mountain where it will be safe.
侠义       胆识       名望...
Code, duty, honor...
我相信这些是值得为之战斗的。
I believe there are things worth fighting for.
制作： EK         时间轴/校对：英文字幕乱翻
第一次做字幕，两天里修改了数十次，翻得不好还请见谅
这剧情也是不忍吐槽...
Someone needs to stop Clearway Law.
Public shouldn't leave reviews for lawyers.